The school festival is over.
I po szkolnym festiwalu.
All that's left is graduation.
Zostało tylko rozdanie świadectw.
During our three years in high school, none of us got a boyfriend.
Przez całe liceum żadna z nas nie miała chłopaka.
Hey, listen! I've got big news!
Hej, słuchajcie! Ważne wieści!
In the staff room, I heard
W pokoju nauczycielskim usłyszałam,
that two girls in our class got referrals to get into Femilia Women's University.
że dwie osoby z naszej klasy dostały listy polecające na Uniwersytet Femilia.
-Really? -No way!
- Naprawdę? - Niemożliwe!
Femilia Women's University?
Uniwersytet Femilia?
That's the school Miho was applying for.
Miho składała tam papiery.
Who's the other one in our class?
Kim jest druga osoba?
I don't know but isn't that bad?
Nie wiem, ale to chyba źle.
Our school is supposed to only get one spot in...
Nasza szkoła ma tylko jedno miejsce...
What?
Co?
Oh, dear. Do you think she heard that?
O nie. Myślicie, że nas słyszała?
It will be fine.
Będzie dobrze.
But what if she heard?
A jeśli słyszała?
Who cares if she heard us?
Kogo to obchodzi?
Who cares? Hurry up and apologize to Miho!
Co za różnica? Przeproś Miho, ale już!
Ayaka.
Ayaka.
This is all a curse by Miho!
To klątwa Miho.
We will all disappear!
Wszystkie znikniemy!
Miho committed suicide because of Okazaki.
Miho popełniła samobójstwo przez Okazakiego.
It wasn't our fault.
To nie nasza wina.
I told you! Miho isn't dead!
Mówiłam wam! Miho żyje!
Are you still saying that?
Czemu dalej tak twierdzisz?
Just accept the reality, would you?
Pogódź się z rzeczywistością.
Your best friend died because of Okazaki!
Twoja przyjaciółka umarła przez Okazakiego,
Miho killed herself when she found that out!
a Miho zabiła się, gdy się o tym dowiedziała!
Cut it out!
Przestań!
Another earthquake?
Kolejne trzęsienie ziemi?
This isn't an earthquake.
To nie trzęsienie.
Then, what is it?
A co?
-I can't take this. -Is everyone okay?
- Nie wytrzymam tego! - Jesteście całe?
I can't take this.
Nie wytrzymam.
Help us.
Pomocy.
Dear God, help us.
Boże, pomocy.
I wonder
- Zastanawiam się... - I guess everything...
if Miho will kill all of us.
- ...czy Miho nas wszystkie zabije. - ...reminds you of something.
Ayaka.
- everything reminds you of something. - Ayaka.
Miho is dead.
Miho nie żyje.
Then, is someone else punishing us in her place?
To dlaczego ktoś karze nas w jej imieniu?
Who would miss Miho the most
Gdyby Miho umarła...
if she died?
kto tęskniłby najbardziej?
Hemingway.
Hemingway.
What?
Co?
Hemingway's death.
Śmierć Hemingwaya.
Do you know how Hemingway died?
Wiecie, jak umarł?
No.
Nie.
He killed himself.
Popełnił samobójstwo.
He killed himself with a shotgun.
Zastrzelił się.
Suicide?
Samobójstwo?
What has Hemingway's suicide got to do with this?
Co samobójstwo Hemingwaya ma wspólnego z nami?
You think we're part of Miho's suicide?
Samobójstwo Miho to nasza wina?
Shut up, would you?
Zamknij się już.
So, what about it?
To o co chodzi?
"Whatever you look at, it reminds you of something."
„Wszystko, co widzimy, z czymś nam się kojarzy”.
The medical instruments in here...
Ten sprzęt medyczny...
But Okazaki had nothing to do with this!
Okazaki nie miał z tym nic wspólnego!
The job of Hemingway's father...
Ojciec Hemingwaya...
What?
Co?
He was a doctor. A famous one.
Był lekarzem. Bardzo znanym.
What is Miho's father's job?
Kim jest ojciec Miho?
Isn't he an assemblyman?
Chyba radnym.
He was the hospital director.
Był dyrektorem szpitala.
Right. He used to be a doctor.
Właśnie. Czyli lekarzem.
The same as Hemingway's family.
Tak samo jak w rodzinie Hemingwaya.
Are you saying Miho's Dad is doing this?
Czyli uwięził nas tu ojciec Miho?
There's no way!
To niemożliwe!
Who cares about this Hemingway stuff?
Kogo obchodzi jakiś Hemingway?
It's just a coincidence.
To przypadek.
There are no coincidences in this room.
W tym pokoju nie ma przypadków.
Everything in this room has meaning.
Wszystko tu ma jakieś znaczenie.
Now, you suspect Miho's dad?
Podejrzewasz ojca Miho?
I can't understand any of this!
Nic z tego nie rozumiem!
What should we apologize for now?
Za co mamy znowu przepraszać?
I don't even know Miho's dad!
Nawet nie znam ojca Miho!
Since Mirei has been telling us to remember stuff,
Ile z nas zniknęło po tym, jak Mirei kazała nam
how many people have vanished?
przypominać sobie różne rzeczy?
-What? -Someone from us might vanish.
- Co? - Ktoś znowu może zniknąć.
After you told us to remember Miho,
Kiedy kazałaś nam przypomnieć sobie sprawę Miho,
Mao, Mei, and Sarina vanished.
zniknęły Mao, Mei i Sarina.
After you told us to remember Perfect,
Gdy powiedziałaś, że mamy przypomnieć sobie Idealną,
Kage and Mr. Hayashi vanished.
zniknęła Kage i pan Hayashi.
When we remembered Okazaki,
Kiedy mówiłyśmy o Okazakim,
Mana and Shiho vanished.
zniknęły Mana i Shiho.
Who will vanish next?
Która zniknie teraz?
Are you saying it's my fault?
Mówisz, że to moja wina?
No!
Nie!
But...
Ale...
I don't want another one of us to vanish.
nie chcę, żeby kolejna osoba zniknęła.
I know how you feel. I feel the same.
Rozumiem, co czujesz. Też tego nie chcę.
But what should we do?
Ale co mamy zrobić?
We need to...
Musimy...
"Whatever you look at, it reminds you of something."
„Wszystko, co widzimy, z czymś nam się kojarzy”.
If we're going to get out of here, that's the answer.
Dzięki temu możemy stąd uciec.
Mr. Hayashi said the same thing.
Pan Hayashi powiedział to samo.
But we don't have to follow it.
Nie musimy go słuchać.
That's right. He could have been lying.
Właśnie. Mógł nas okłamać.
I can't be wrong!
Nie mylę się!
Then,
Skoro tak,
should we have
może powinnyśmy były
just sat here quietly?
po prostu siedzieć tu w ciszy?
But many have disappeared already...
Ale wiele z nas już zniknęło.
They deserved to have disappeared!
Zasłużyły na to!
They deserved it?
Zasłużyły?
They vanished after confessing their sins!
Zniknęły po tym, jak wyznały grzechy.
What did Mana do wrong? She just fell in love with a guy!
Jaki był grzech Many? Tylko się zakochała.
How should I know?
Skąd mam wiedzieć?
Anyway, we haven't done anything wrong.
My nie zrobiłyśmy nic złego.
-You bullied Miho! -We all did!
- Dręczyłaś Miho! - Jak każda z nas!
-I didn't bully her! -Isn't a crime to turn a blind eye?
- Ja nie! - Ale nie reagowałaś. To prawie to samo.
A best friend wouldn't do that.
Przyjaciółka by się tak nie zachowała.
You said you know Miho the best.
Mówiłaś, że znasz Miho najlepiej.
If you had helped Miho, none of this would have ever happened!
Gdybyś jej pomogła, nic by się nie wydarzyło!
It's all your fault, idiot! Admit it!
To twoja wina, idiotko! Przyznaj się!
You should just disappear!
Powinnaś zniknąć!
Kyoko.
Kyoko.
It's getting hot.
Robi się gorąco.
Shichiro Watanabe.
Shichiro Watanabe.
Prefectural assemblyman.
Radny prefektury.
Boss of the prefectural assembly.
Przewodniczący rady.
I don't want to sit here and do nothing!
Nie chcę tu bezczynnie siedzieć
I don't want to just wait here to die!
i czekać na śmierć!
Shichiro Watanabe.
Shichiro Watanabe.
Prefectural assemblyman.
Radny prefektury.
Boss of the prefectural assembly.
Przewodniczący rady.
Director of the biggest general hospital in the prefecture.
Dyrektor największego szpitala w prefekturze.
But
Ale...
due to suspicions that arose,
usunięto go z tych stanowisk...
those positions were taken away from him.
w związku z podejrzeniami, jakie wokół niego narosły.
Isn't that right, Kumi?
Prawda, Kumi?
Well, I don't know about those suspicions.
Nie wiem nic o tych podejrzeniach.
I ignored them.
Ignorowałam je.
I heard he controlled the port and the harbor.
Podobno kontrolował port i przystań.
I heard nobody in town could defy Miho's dad.
Ponoć nikt w mieście nie mógł mu się sprzeciwić.
Miho was able to get away with all those dangerous things
Miho mogła bezkarnie robić te niebezpieczne rzeczy
because her father had so much power.
dzięki wpływom swojego ojca.
That's why we did whatever Miho told us.
I dlatego robiłyśmy to, co nam kazała.
Then, as soon as her dad lost his power,
A kiedy jej ojciec stracił władzę, wszyscy zwrócili się
everyone started bullying Miho.
przeciwko Miho.
I bet he was involved in shady stuff.
Pewnie prowadził szemrane interesy.
I heard he got bribes from construction companies,
Podobno przyjmował łapówki od firm budowlanych
and controlled all the jobs at the port and harbor.
i obsadzał wszystkie stanowiska w porcie i przystani.
But none of that stuff has anything to do with us.
Ale to nie ma z nami nic wspólnego.
I heard about illegitimate children.
Słyszałam, że miał nieślubne dzieci.
You mean, Miho had siblings?
Miho miała rodzeństwo?
-Did Miho know about that? -I never heard about it.
- Wiedziała o tym? - Nic nie wspominała.
She may have known, but kept quiet about it.
Może wiedziała, ale milczała.
I guess.
Możliwe.
Even if you're friends, you can't always talk about everything.
Nawet przyjaciółkom nie mówi się o wszystkim.
I wonder what Miho's dad did about her suicide.
Ciekawe, co ojciec Miho zrobił w związku z jej samobójstwem.
What do you mean?
Co masz na myśli?
I mean, nobody knew about it.
Nikt się o tym nie dowiedział.
I wonder if he was worried that it might affect his image and hid her suicide.
Może to zataił, bo martwił się, że wpłynie to na jego wizerunek.
But he wasn't a bad guy.
Ale nie był złym człowiekiem.
He sent medicine to children in poor countries.
Wysyłał leki dzieciom z biednych krajów.
Anyway, he was kind. He had a strong sense of responsibility.
Był uprzejmy i odpowiedzialny.
I think Miho must have started Perfect because she admired her dad.
Myślę, że Miho wymyśliła Idealną dlatego, że podziwiała ojca.
Did Miho and her dad get along?
Dobrze się dogadywali?
They used to get along.
Kiedyś tak.
But lately,
Ale ostatnio mówiła,
she said that when she wasn't around, her dad was more at ease.
że ojciec czuje się lepiej, kiedy nie ma jej w pobliżu.
I wonder if something happened between her and her dad.
Zastanawiam się, co między nimi zaszło.
-I never asked. -But wasn't Miho's suicide
- Nigdy nie spytałam. - Ale czy Miho nie zabiła się
caused by the medical error at her dad's hospital?
z powodu błędu medycznego w szpitalu jej ojca?
If he hadn't covered up what Okazaki did,
Gdyby nie zatuszował tego, co zrobił Okazaki,
Miho may not have killed herself.
może nadal by żyła.
If his daughter's death was his own fault,
Jeśli Miho zabiła się przez niego,
why is he getting revenge on us?
dlaczego mści się na nas?
I thought the same thing.
O tym samym pomyślałam.
That's why Miho's dad couldn't be the one doing this.
Dlatego to nie może być jej ojciec.
So, there's another reason unrelated to Miho?
Czyli jest jakaś przyczyna, która nie ma związku z Miho?
Well, I mean,
Cóż...
I've never met Miho's dad.
Nigdy nie poznałam jej ojca.
I have.
Ja poznałam.
At school.
W szkole.
Miho's dad?
Ojca Miho?
Why?
Dlaczego?
He met with Mr. Hayashi.
Spotykał się z panem Hayashim.
He met Hayashi?
Z Hayashim?
You know that he always asked me to stay for remedial lessons, right?
Pan Hayashi zawsze kazał mi zostawać na zajęciach wyrównawczych.
I saw him several times then.
Na nich widywałam ojca Miho.
I asked Mr. Hayashi about it.
Spytałam o to pana Hayashiego.
He said he was asking him for advice about his family life.
Powiedział, że ojciec Miho prosi go o porady rodzinne.
He didn't give me any details though.
Nie znam szczegółów.
Maybe Mr. Hayashi was here at the request of Miho's dad.
Może pan Hayashi przyszedł tutaj na prośbę ojca Miho?
-That could be. -You mean Mr. Hayashi was paid off?
- Możliwe. - Czyli mu zapłacono?
That's a possibility.
To możliwe.
Adults are so deceitful.
Dorośli są tacy podstępni.
We should have taught Miho's dad a lesson too.
Ojcu Miho też trzeba było dać nauczkę.
What do you mean?
Co masz na myśli?
With Perfect.
Idealną.
Perfect?
Idealną?
Even after Miho's Perfect ended,
Nawet po rozwiązaniu Idealnej
we kept doing deeds for justice.
dalej wymierzałyśmy sprawiedliwość.
Party companions. Sugar daddies. Hostess clubs.
Prostytutki, sponsorzy, kluby z hostessami.
We did all of them.
Nie przestałyśmy.
Yes.
To prawda.
There are tons of disgusting guys out there.
Świat jest pełen obrzydliwych typów.
Guys who go after young girls the age of their own daughters.
Facetów, którzy podrywają dziewczyny w wieku własnych córek.
We punished those kinds of jerks.
Karałyśmy takich drani.
Punished them?
Karałyście?
Ayaka was the decoy who would draw them out.
Ayaka była przynętą.
She would take them to a street of sleazy hotels, and I'd photograph them.
Zabierała ich na ulicę pełną podejrzanych hoteli, a ja robiłam typom zdjęcia.
You blackmailed them?
Szantażowałyście ich?
Some even wept. "Please, don't tell anyone!"
Niektórzy błagali, żeby nikomu nie mówić.
That's dangerous.
To niebezpieczne.
We don't do it anymore.
Już tego nie robimy.
I'll admit, we had some close calls.
Ale przyznam, że bywało groźnie.
Don't tell me you threatened them for money!
Nie mów, że groziłyście im dla pieniędzy.
I never asked for money. They just gave it to me on their own!
Nie żądałam pieniędzy. Czasem sami mi je dawali!
Kyoko.
Kyoko.
-Actually, -What?
- Właściwie... - Co?
I kept doing it for a while after that.
Ja działałam trochę dłużej.
Did what?
Działałaś gdzie?
-Perfect. -What?
- W Idealnej. - Co?
You punished guys on your own?
Sama karałaś ludzi?
Why didn't you tell me until now?
Czemu mówisz mi dopiero teraz?
But I've stopped now.
Już tego nie robię.
Were you all right?
Nic ci się nie stało?
There was a weird guy once.
Raz spotkałam dziwnego typa.
-What? A weird guy? -No! Not that kind of weird.
- „Dziwnego”? Zboczeńca? - Nie o to chodzi.
He came alone to a party and kept asking me questions
Przyszedł na imprezę sam i pytał mnie
about my family life, my parents' income, how I get allowance, and some other stuff.
o moje życie rodzinne, zarobki rodziców, skąd mam pieniądze i tym podobne.
Come to think of it, Mana had a lighter.
Pamiętacie? Mana miała zapalniczkę.
Yes.
Tak.
You mean Mana did the same kind of work?
Czyli ona robiła to samo?
I introduced her to it.
Ja ją wprowadziłam.
Really?
Naprawdę?
She's so innocent.
Ta niewinna dziewczyna?
She got interested when I said the money was good.
Przekonały ją dobre zarobki.
Who cares? What happened with that guy?
Co za różnica? O co chodziło z tym typem?
When we walked towards a hotel, he said,
Kiedy wyszliśmy, zapytał,
"Are you trying to take me to a hotel?"
czy zamierzam zabrać go do hotelu.
He got angry and scolded me.
Wkurzył się i na mnie nakrzyczał.
Then what happened?
I co dalej?
He asked if I was hungry, and took me to a family restaurant.
Spytał, czy jestem głodna, i zabrał mnie do restauracji.
-Then, he gave me money. -What?
- Potem dał mi pieniądze. - Co?
He said, "I'll give you money, but don't ever do this again."
Powiedział, że da mi je, jeśli przestanę to robić.
He thought I was selling my body.
Myślał, że sprzedaję swoje ciało.
He said he had a daughter about my age.
Powiedział, że ma córkę w moim wieku.
In fact, he asked me for help with her.
Prosił, bym mu pomogła.
He said he loved her dearly, but she had matured so quickly,
Mówił, że bardzo ją kocha, ale ona tak szybko dorosła,
he couldn't talk to her anymore.
że nie wie, jak z nią rozmawiać.
He was desperate to find a way to talk to her.
Był zdesperowany, żeby jakoś do niej dotrzeć.
I realized that even adults have problems.
Wtedy zrozumiałam, że nawet dorośli mają problemy.
Why the heck did he go to one of those parties anyway?
Po co w ogóle chodził na takie imprezy?
He said he wanted to know how girls his daughter's age felt,
Chciał zrozumieć, jak czują się dziewczyny w wieku jego córki.
and it was also for his work.
Chodziło też o pracę.
Work?
Pracę?
He said it was a poverty inquiry.
Mówił, że chodzi o badania nad biedą.
I realized they aren't all disgusting.
Zrozumiałam, że to nie są sami zboczeńcy.
Some men are like him.
Niektórzy są tacy jak on.
-Since then... -Hold on.
- Od tego czasu... - Czekaj.
What's with you?
O co ci chodzi?
Look at this photo.
Spójrz na to zdjęcie.
Who is this?
Kto to?
Miho's dad.
Ojciec Miho.
Miho's dad was always giving aid to young women
Ojciec Miho zawsze pomagał młodym kobietom
to improve their living conditions.
polepszać warunki ich życia.
He went around asking about their lifestyle.
Wypytywał o to, jak żyją.
Really?
Naprawdę?
It wasn't Miho's dad that you met, was it?
To nie jego spotkałaś, prawda?
-I don't know. -What?
- Nie wiem. - Co?
There's no way I can tell.
Nie mam pojęcia.
You're lying.
Kłamiesz.
There's no way I could remember some guy's face.
Nie pamiętam twarzy przypadkowych mężczyzn.
Can you?
Ty byś pamiętała?
I don't know!
Nie wiem!
Another tweet from Perfect.
Kolejny tweet na Idealnej.
-You're right. -I see it too.
- Faktycznie. - Też go widzę.
-Me too. -Call for help first!
- I ja. - Dzwoń po pomoc!
CALLING
ŁĄCZENIE
NO SIGNAL
BRAK SYGNAŁU
Damn it!
Cholera!
YOU HAVE A NEW MESSAGE.
MASZ NOWĄ WIADOMOŚĆ
It's no good. I can't connect to the Wi-Fi.
To na nic. Nie mogę się połączyć z wi-fi.
Me neither.
Ja też nie.
I can still access Twitter.
Ale mogę wejść na Twittera.
PERFECT JUSTICE
IDEALNA SPRAWIEDLIWOŚĆ
This is Miho's dad, right?
To ojciec Miho, prawda?
Miho's dad was photographed by a gossip magazine
Plotkarski magazyn zrobił mu zdjęcie,
walking with an underage girl near some sleazy hotels.
kiedy szedł z nieletnią dziewczyną do szemranego hotelu.
There were many suspicions about him, but this was the cause of his downfall.
Krążyło wokół niego wiele podejrzeń, ale ta kropla przepełniła czarę.
Isn't this the bag
Czy to nie jest...
that I gave you?
torebka ode mnie?
I get it now.
Już rozumiem.
-What is it? -I understand everything now.
- Co? - Wszystko rozumiem.
-What? -You were getting revenge on Miho.
- Mściłaś się na Miho.
What do you mean?
Co masz na myśli?
You lied earlier.
Kłamałaś wcześniej.
-I lied? -Kyoko,
- Co? - Kyoko,
you said you distanced yourself from Miho, right?
mówiłaś, że odsunęłaś się od Miho, prawda?
-Yes. -But
- Tak. - Ale...
after that, you went back to Perfect.
potem wróciłaś do Idealnej.
Isn't that right?
Prawda?
Explain yourself.
Wytłumacz się.
If you won't say it, I will.
Jeśli sama tego nie powiesz, ja to zrobię.
Miho saw you two kissing.
Miho widziała, jak się całujecie.
Then Miho told you,
Powiedziała ci,
"I know you two are dating.
że wie o waszym związku.
If you don't want your parents to know, return to Perfect."
„Wróć do Idealnej albo twoi rodzice się dowiedzą”.
Dating?
Jakim związku?
What are you talking about?
O czym ty mówisz?
Ayaka and I are just friends.
Ayaka i ja się przyjaźnimy.
Right, Ayaka?
Prawda, Ayaka?
-It's too late for that. -What?
- Już za późno. - Co?
Everyone here knows that you two are dating.
Wszystkie tu wiemy, że jesteście razem.
In fact, the whole class knew.
Cała klasa wiedziała.
Since Miho had you under her thumb,
Miho miała na was haka,
you wanted to do something to put her in a fix.
więc chciałyście się jej pozbyć.
-What? -So you came up with this idea.
- Co? - Dlatego wymyśliłaś ten plan.
You set a honey trap for Miho's dad since he was her source of power.
Złapałaś ojca Miho w sidła, bo to dzięki niemu miała władzę.
-Are you kidding me? -Mirei.
- Żartujesz sobie? - Mirei.
Ayaka knew that Miho's dad was going to that party.
Ayaka wiedziała, że ojciec Miho będzie na imprezie.
Then Ayaka invited Miho's dad to a hotel, then a gossip magazine
Potem zaprosiła go do hotelu, żeby magazyn
got photos of him and you.
mógł zrobić zdjęcia.
Thanks to that, Miho's dad lost his position,
Dzięki temu ojciec Miho stracił stanowisko,
and everyone started bullying her.
a ona sama zaczęła być nękana.
Everything went exactly according to your plan.
Wszystko poszło zgodnie z planem.
-What? -What a load of bullshit!
- Co? - Co to za bzdury?
Is that true?
To prawda?
Of course it isn't!
Pewnie, że nie!
Mirei, don't make those assumptions on your own.
Mirei, nie wymyślaj takich rzeczy.
I didn't assume those! It's the truth!
Niczego nie wymyślam. To prawda!
What are you talking about?
O czym ty mówisz?
Hurry up and confess!
Szybko, przyznaj się!
Miho's dad, hurry up and make these two disappear.
Tato Miho, szybko, niech one znikną!
Then let the rest of us go!
A potem wypuść resztę.
Mirei,
Mirei,
have you lost your mind?
zwariowałaś?
Fine!
Dobrze!
The girl in this photo,
Dziewczyna na zdjęciu
it's me.
to ja.
Is that so?
Tak?
My thoughtless actions
Moje bezmyślne działanie
caused trouble for Miho's dad. I apologize for that.
przysporzyło ojcu Miho problemów. Przepraszam.
But it wasn't on purpose.
Ale nie zrobiłam tego specjalnie.
I honestly didn't know it was Miho's dad!
Nawet nie wiedziałam, że to ojciec Miho.
Mirei, let's believe her.
Mirei, uwierzmy jej.
That's right.
Właśnie.
There's water.
Woda.
There's water!
Woda!
Ayaka!
Ayaka!
I am...
Teraz...
going to vanish.
ja zniknę.
It's okay.
Wszystko będzie dobrze.
I won't let go of your hand!
Nie puszczę cię!
I'm sorry.
Przepraszam.
I...
Mnie...
didn't care about Perfect Justice.
nie interesowała Idealna Sprawiedliwość.
I just wanted additional income.
Chciałam tylko trochę zarobić.
Why?
Po co?
We made a promise.
Obiecałyśmy sobie...
"Let's live together
że po zakończeniu szkoły
after graduating."
zamieszkamy razem.
I saved up money.
Odkładałam pieniądze.
We can always be together from now on.
Miałyśmy już na zawsze być razem.
Ayaka!
Ayaka!
THIS DRAMA IS A WORK OF FICTION.
PRZEDSTAWIONY SERIAL JEST FIKCJĄ.
Subtitle translation by Brian Athey
Napisy: Arianna Sugier